a new architecture for AI much more
powerful than llms is about to come into
the world it's called active
inference there's been a lot of
discussion in the AI Community about the
need for a new architecture and AI
paradigm shift to continue evolving the
technology just this morning heavy
discussion was sparked online about a
paper that was published in Sage
journals in October the centered around
what children can do that large language
and language in Vision models
cannot this paper argues that the best
way to think about these systems is as
powerful new cultural Technologies but
that they lack the ability to innovate
llms do not have the ability to actually
perceive the world and act on it in new
ways it's the difference between
imitation and
Innovation as this paper points out
nothing in their training or objective
functions is designed to fulfill the act
of Truth seeking such as perception
causal inference or Theory formation so
why is this I encourage you to tune in
to this episode of my podcast
conversation with Mal alasen director of
product for research and Innovation at
versus AI as we explore a critical piece
that is missing in current AI models a
sense of
self so what does this mean and how do
active inference intelligent agents
achieve this sense of themselves in the
world and what does this mean for the
evolution of cognitive
Technologies as we Marvel at the prowess
of pre-trained Transformer models like
chat GPT Claude and others it's time to
investigate a bit further and seek
answers beyond the hype and Fascination
lies a catalyst for Change and
remarkable Innovation fundamentally
redefining what AI
means this is active inference AI when
we talk about about llms what we're
really talking about is content to
content prediction what you're getting
is a piece of content that doesn't
intrinsically have any meaning right
it's just a piece of content that
generally is placed in a hierarchy of
other contents and what you're going to
do is predict the most likely x amount
of word given the the the selected words
given an attention Paradigm and that's
super useful it's very um it's very
efficient for tasks that do not require
a lot of cognition they require
hardcoded knowledge in a sense we
generally use active inference to talk
about living organisms self-organizing
organisms so that includes humans but
eventually that could include AI systems
because um the key part of living is
mostly
self-organization and so basically what
we do is that we perceive information
and then we act in the world by
constantly making predictions about our
environment based on the outcomes of our
actions and so then we update these
predictions based on the sensory input
that returns from our actions as well it
would involve a continuous cycle of
hypothesis testing which is not
something llms currently do llms when
they are giving you an output have no
sense of themselves in the world they do
not
understand what they're saying or what
the outcome of what they're saying is
going to be and where they are relative
to what they were asked they don't have
a sense of self so then they don't
really update their internal model based
on the prediction errors most of these
systems are static so now let's say you
gave an llm um the capacity to
continuously update all right so that's
a step forward right you would have the
capacity to um enable the system to
adapt a little bit more but it would
kind of adapt blindly because again
active inference is related to the
boundary of the system and the
relationship between the the internal um
states of the system and the external
world this join distribution is Central
it's key to have a sense of this joint
distribution you need to have a sense of
perspective you need to have a sense of
self relative to the world and to what
enables you to fulfill your goals and
once you have all of that then you have
um a sense of B
a sense that gives you um a position
into the world with that position you
can now predict the outcomes of your
actions and understand where you are
relative to the request to the input to
what you are trying to do I think that's
what's missing
currently
[Music]
hi and welcome back to another episode
of the spatial web AI podcast today I
have a wonderful guest with me um ma
alasen Mao is the director of product
for research and Innovations in active
inference ma thank you so much for
coming on our show today it's such a
pleasure to have you here um why don't
you introduce yourself to our audience
uh and kind of give them an idea of of
what kind of work you're involved in
sure so thanks for having me um I am in
fact director of product for research
Innovations but I'm also um doing a PhD
in cognitive Computing I have a masters
in social sciences I'm affiliated with
the institute for health and society and
uh for the institute for feminist
research at ukam which is the university
in Montreal uh the work I do generally
touch is on uh social systems
simulations and how you can predict and
understand belief changes given certain
kinds of semantic or meaning fields that
are shared across different groups and
how those can evolve over
time very nice very nice well um I'm so
excited to dive into this conversation
with you today um before we get started
down the path of active inference though
you know what a bombshell we just had
this week weekend with open Ai and Sam
Altman and all of that um do you have
any thoughts you'd like to share since I
know it's top of mind for everybody
right now right so I guess everybody's
going to be a little worried about the
future of open Ai and about the future
of their tools that were being widely
used by everybody I think the key
question is one what is going to happen
to the open source model uh and what is
going to happen uh to the nonprofit
aspect of open a at least as it was
stated before um but beyond this this
seems more like
um political battle like it seems to be
about certain kinds of decisions that
were internally not fully aligned um I
think we as people who work in the field
have to stay focused and stay focused
specifically
on what do we want for the world what we
want for the future how are we sourcing
uh those directions uh instead of
focusing on one entrepreneur or one of
the tools there are many people giving
thoughts to these ideas and I think we
should mostly be worried about a large
Monopoly that may not be giving us uh
the tools to potentially influence where
these kinds of questions are going
Microsoft is a wonderful company it does
uh tremendous work but it is one big
company we really need to to make sure
that there is a plethora of approaches
to this very same problem such that we
don't necessarily fall into a dip and
then consider that this is the only
approach we should be using yeah totally
agree with that um you know one of the
thoughts that I had you know just a
couple days before all this started you
know Sam became very vocal about llms
can't lead to AGI so my I'm just so
curious what their research will lean to
now so yeah those are things that I've
been thinking about so that's actually a
really interesting question I think we
we tend to think of AI as the tool but
for now ai is the expertise what matters
is who the people you have understand of
the field and how they manage to
innovate and build upon past knowledge
so it doesn't really matter whether they
use GPT or not what matters is what are
the people that were brought over there
understanding of what's required to move
forward and if if you if you are correct
about what Salon Alman is saying that
llms will not bring us to AGI I think I
think we all kind of knew that it's not
sufficient to have a very very
proficient language model because while
Mo language is an intrinsic part of our
cognition it is not sufficient um
because for instance um if
you re if you put the words in a
different order the if you scrambled the
um
um the probabilities in the models you
wouldn't have a different cognition
right you would just have nonsense um
what you need is a model that's capable
of understanding a structure of the
world there's a notion of understanding
here that cannot simply be latent in the
static knowledge that captured by
probabilities of language great Point um
so that brings me then to uh you know
the most exciting aspect of me having
you on the show is let's dive into uh
let's dive into a little bit the the
difference between the llms and the
active inference and what is your
opinion on why you know active inference
is uh likely to play a hugely pivotal
role in the future of AI okay so um when
we talk about llms what we're really
talking about is content to content
prediction what you're getting is a
piece of content that doesn't
intrinsically have any meaning right
it's just a piece of content that
generally is placed in a hierarchy of
other contents and what you're going to
do is predict the most likely x amount
of word given the the the selected words
given an attention Paradigm and that's
super useful it's very um it's very
efficient for tasks that do not require
a lot of cognition they require
hardcoded knowledged in a sense so when
we think about intelligence we can think
of crystallized intelligence so just
knowledge if I ask you a trivia question
can you give me back the answer to that
trivia question it's different say from
an IQ test where it's not all about
knowledge it's mostly about your
capacity to derive the structure of a
problem which is something an llm cannot
do you need to be able to understand how
different pieces interact with each
other and understand the deeper
foundations that might give to a
prediction um and potentially even a
volatile environment prediction so not
I've seen this before and therefore I
can reproduce it now it's more I have
never seen this before but it follows
certain kinds of patterns that I might
have encountered or if I combine these
two things together I'm going to infer
given their properties a new type of
property and and that's how I'm going to
move towards uh a new prediction so
that's roughly why active inference or
at least least model-based approaches
lead us to potentially closer to what we
consider to be
AGI interesting yeah so what you're
touching on there then in in that
explanation is how our our brains work
with the free energy principle
predicting rationalizing the cause of
what we're we're interpreting through
our sensory input and and then measuring
it against what we know to be true in in
the this internal model we've already
you know established and then correcting
from there you know I mean that's the
basic way that I I try to explain this
to people but I'm sure you can do a much
better job than me and I would love to
hear how you would explain the free
energy principle to somebody here sure
so I'm going to explain the difference
between LMS and and and active inference
and that's going to allow us to dig into
the free energy principle so sure um LM
is basically designed to is for for
generating and manipulating just human
language right they are trained on a
vast amount of data uh to predict the
next word in a sentence um essentially
you have supervised learning over a
large Corpus of text uh so they learn
just statistical patterns just
statistical patterns um and which is
just essentially adjusting weights in
the neural network to op to minimize the
difference between the predicted output
and the actual output so this sounds
very similar to what we think we're
doing with active inference right we're
just trying to minimize difference
between um an input or a predicted
output and the actual
output um the the in active inference
though there's a little bit more going
on under the hood so basically we have
we generally use active inference to
talk about living organisms
self-organizing organisms so that
includes humans but eventually that
could include AI systems because um the
key part of living is mostly
self-organization it doesn't require the
system to bre brief it does require the
system to try to maintain its current
state space let's say the the way that
it's uh distributed over SpaceTime um
and so basically what we do is that we
perceive information and then we act in
the world by constantly making
predictions about our environment based
on the outcomes of our actions and so
then we update these predictions based
on the sensory input that returns from
our actions as well um so
like difference isn't just a specific
model it's a theory about how
intelligence systems could operate you
could have an llm that uses active
inference but it would involve a
continuous cycle of hypothesis testing
which is not something llms currently do
llms when they are giving you an output
have no sense of themselves in the world
they do not
understand what they're saying or what
the outcome of what they're saying is
going to be and where they are relative
to what they were asked um they don't
have a sense of self um so then they
don't really update their internal model
based on the prediction errors most of
these systems are static so now let's
say you gave an llm um the capacity to
continuously update all right so that's
a step forward right you would have the
capacity to um enable the system to
adapt a little bit more but it would
kind of adapt blindly because again
active inference is related to the
boundary of the system and the
relationship between the the internal um
states of the system and the external
world this join distribution is Central
it's key to have a sense of this joint
distribution you need to have a sense of
perspective you need to have a sense of
self relative to the world and to what
enables you to fulfill your goals and
once you you have all of that then you
have um a sense of bias a sense that
gives you um a position into the world
with that position you can now predict
the outcomes of your actions and
understand where you are relative to the
request to the input to what you are
trying to do I think that's what's
missing currently it doesn't have to be
done through the free energy principle
um so the free energy principle is it's
quite simple in itself it's simply
saying um you're trying to minimize a
quantity known as free energy which in
terms of information is just surprise
you are trying to put yourself in a
place where you are likely to continue
existing and therefore self-evidence in
this way you want to make sure you're
constantly in a place where nothing is
going to come and disrupt your boundary
you can only do this by continuously
learning
and by you know exploiting your
environment so you're trading off
constantly between exploring and
exploiting um interesting yeah I love
this I also love the point of it
requires a sense of self because that's
something that I hadn't uh really put
together and that that that kind of
brings it all together in the sense of
why why these other systems aren't
capable of that wow
okay so another question then um because
I know you know I know you work closely
with Carl Carl friston uh what is it
like to work with
Carl I know there's going to be people
out there that are wondering just like I
am so he is one of my PhD advisers um
he's a very nice man very British and uh
I think it's mostly a Wonder to watch
him anytime we're in a meeting um you
know how somebody will have an answer
for you when you ask a question and you
can sort of
quantify how well they know a topic
given how long they can talk about
anything when you ask them a question or
pay attention to the tiny details of
what you said Carl will essentially not
only understand every word that you said
have something to say about every word
that you said but also be capable of
derive insights that you didn't have um
and constantly make connections among
the different fields that he is
um I I don't really know the term but um
touching on he he he he's an expert in
many many fields and he knows a lot of
researchers which he's in constant
contact with um and so it's uh it's
quite inspiring to see the bre breadth
and depth of knowledge that he has what
led you down this
road so I it's really interesting
question I came from social sciences and
um I thought that was my calling I
wanted to help people I wanted
to understand in depth the complexities
of the human mind and the complexities
of the world and I thought the best way
of doing that was to talk was to hear
people and to derive meaning from the
connections that they make and through
this Mosaic you would get the full
picture and while that is
sort of true um there was something
missing I tried to I I I would read
different paradigms and it would see
consistent patterns with that seemed
confluent they seemed to go in same
direction there was something that
everyone was touching on and when I
tried to put this together I tried to
show look it's the same thing is being
talked about in all of these fields the
response from the field was often no
these are incompatible paradigms we are
not uh using the same terms or if we are
they don't mean the same thing therefore
it would take you years and years and
years and years to really put these
things together and that that that
seemed like nonsense to me to me it
seemed like no like it's clear you can
see it you just have to just formulate
what is common and try to weed out the
other things that may seem um a little
Divergent but really could be construed
as noise um or perhaps not noise but
scale
specific and my teachers weren't
listening to me so I started talking to
other people I started reading and um at
some point A friend of mine was like
well why don't you talk to a professor
to do a PhD in in Computing which seemed
to be the direction I was getting
interested in and I thought that was
impossible because someone in social
sciences can't go into confu Computing
turns out you can turns out you you just
have to you know pull your bootstraps
and Learn Python and start reading a lot
and uh I spoke to a wonderful professor
professor Pi at ukam who is open-minded
who understood the same theories as I
did which was a boon and absolute
miracle and he led me to Maxwell
ramstead who was basically doing very
similar research to what I was doing or
at least to my interests and together
developed the formalism I had in mind
and found that it was in fact uh
possible to link the several theories I
was trying to link together through the
active inflence formalism so what what
are the separate theories that you were
linking together so um I was mostly
looking into scripts Theory um and if
you know scripts Theory it's been used
by many many fields in many different
ways um I was leveraging b gothman g
Simon I was also leveraging Butler and
all of
these draw from different um conceptual
approaches ablon as well some of them
come from very analytical Fields some of
them come from Continental fields and in
the Continental Fields there are
different schools of thought that seem
relatively incompatible and in fact my
contention is they want to be
incompatible like for instance um Butler
draws from laon with draws from
psychoanalysis um Simo G do not they
generally steer away from these theories
uh they're more sociological they try
not to pathologize in the same way and
they they try to reside in the
blurriness there is an actual desire to
remain um non-materialist and
potentially also um non-positivist so we
try not
to Define fine outside of a context
right and and that's fine but it does
cause some blurriness and that
blurriness makes it so that sometimes
it's impossible it seems impossible to
connect different approaches but what I
like to think of this contextuality as
this blurriness as is just a
distribution you're not you don't have
the certainty of a specific um outcome
you don't have the certainty of a
specific definition you have a
distribution over something that
resembles a prototype if you don't want
to say phenotype and that prototype
generally allows for different clusters
to connect maybe not perfectly but still
connect and s in such a way what you can
do is understand how one mapping can go
to another mapping um and if you can
quantify these things then you have uh
the possibility to communicate among the
different paradigms and um make sure
that a specific content concept that may
not be contained in one of the paradigms
can either find a proper mapping or
understand how it moves the
distributions across the other Paradigm
if I don't have this specific context
concept how does it allow this
distribution to shift a little
bit very interesting so so
then obviously that leads into you
progressing into this space of active
inference research so maybe tell me a
little bit how those findings LED you
into this space you said you you met
Maxwell and then you guys kind of
partnered up in your research so maybe
uh talk a little bit about how that
played out right so Maxwell was um
already very connected and he had done a
lot of research in the field of um
social cognition under active imprints
in fact he was one of the pioneers of um
multiscale active inference which means
it can go from cells all the way to
groups right and what I started doing is
discuss the exact semantics the social
semantics of these um of these groups
and how those might evolve over time or
how those might influence specific types
of group dynamics such as uh the ICS of
gender or um the specific uh script
formulation or even how you can get a
Twitter Echo chamber um through these
collaborations we found that there was
something to pull on and and something
bigger than just um active inference or
these specific ideas while we started
thinking through what what does it mean
to have an agent we started
understanding that intelligence is not a
function of one actor intelligence is a
function of a of a group dynamic it's
about how much information you can ACR
and leverage given your relationships
with the rest of the world and how that
can lead you to either um gain more
knowledge and grow to a potential
emergent feature or how that can lead
you very much astray given the wrong
Dynamics or at least dynamics that are
not conducive to the survival of either
your group or you and so um now this
leads us to understanding how AI really
probably shouldn't be um unitary concept
it shouldn't be one AI it shouldn't be
uh one approach it really should be
collections of agents that are capable
of sharing information from multiple
perspectives such that not one
perspective gets erased but they are
capable of dynamically self-organizing
in a harmonious way and dis Haron leads
us to potentially what we understand AS
Global alignment humans do this all the
time we're not perfect at it we still
have wars we still have conflict but
through the agglomeration of people with
relatively similar models or at least
similar goals we are capable of
cooperating we are capable of growing
and getting more knowledge and acing
more resources given our common
coordination so we believe that by
understanding these fundamental
processes and couching them in physics
math formalism but also leveraging all
the insights the the really important
insights from social sciences we will be
able to derive a safer better um AI
approach yeah you know that's one of the
things that really struck me in the
white paper you know about the
distributed intelligence um because you
know to me it that makes complete sense
because that is how knowledge Grows
Right you know knowledge doesn't grow
from one person or one entity it takes
all of the it it depends on the
diversity of Intelligence coming from
all the different frames of reference
and sharing information and then you
have actual you know Global Knowledge
coming out of that you know um so yeah
that that to me is one of the things
that that um I I definitely see in the
research that you're doing as being
hugely important and I think that goes
back to what we were talking about
earlier in the you know these these uh
llms or in even just within the Deep
learning sphere you have these
monolithic systems that are just trained
top down on large amounts of data but
it's just a singular
system you're not going to get knowledge
growing out of that it just
it's not absolutely essentially one of
the issues with the current llms is
that you get a lot of knowledge in it
but it's not anchored it's not it
doesn't tell you anything about a given
context it only gives you as much as the
attention mechanisms give you um but
what you need is to understand what
knowledge is relevant for what purpose
it's it's the connection it's the vector
from um cognition to action um given an
objective that is useful right because
what that's that's why trivia doesn't
work for me I don't can't do trivia
because to me trivia is just just Sparks
of nothingness being pulled out of the
ether it's it's it's it doesn't connect
to anything but if you were to ask
somebody to pull this knowledge for a
purpose in a context they probably know
the answer yeah resonates with me
because you know I I can totally see
that about trivia you know it's just
irrelevant it's just you know random
bits of information that might answer
the question that was asked but what
relevance does it have to anything
beyond that moment you know no precisely
your brain isn't even in that space I
mean your brain is not primed for
anything at that point so that's that's
I mean that's part of the challenge
obviously but to me it seems like a very
very difficult challenge compared to ask
me the same question in the right
context and I will have the answer for
you and I think that's the the problem
you're doing with LMS right now with
llms right now you're like asking them
trivia questions as opposed to putting
them in the right context aiming them in
the right direction and now answer the
question um context is gonna change the
answer that's right exactly and and in
Your Capacity also to derive the um the
underlying physics or or the the
mechanisms in the context that give rise
to the knowledge being the right one
that's also part of what's
required very interesting so I would
love to know your thoughts on where do
you see this research taking us in the
realm of AI and the future of of this
next era of AI because I think you know
like we touched on earlier there is a
consensus that you know there's a new
architecture that's required Beyond
these uh llms and these monolithic forms
of of synthetic intelligence where do
you see this taking us and and what do
you see uh being the the the biggest
impact like on uh on people and our
interaction with these intelligent
agents you know in our lives over time
you know like the next five years 10
years so it depends what we what we
adopt if we adopt an active influence
approach with agents that are
distributed um what I expect is that we
will it seems It's it seems a little bit
grandstanding but um evolve to the next
level so what do I mean by that
currently we are on the edge of
emergence right we can feel it there's
something unsettled there seems to be
some more integration happening except
it's not happen happening in anyone's
mind per se it's happening at higher
super structures like institutions Etc
so we we're like coming to this Edge now
what I think this is going to allow us
to do is have a representation of us is
not limited necessarily by our physical
constraints but that can pull from the
information of the other um people in
the world and that is capable of feeding
as well into this sort of um strata that
that has the capacity to integrate the
information but also be pulled down
since the the integrated information
does get used by the individual agents
so that means that we're going to get
prores of Agents just like we have now
except these agents are going to speak
the same language and be able to derive
insights from each other which isn't
currently necessarily the case like for
instance I don't speak legales I can't
derive insights from there and even if
the legal system were to try to
communicate with me which it can't right
the legal system isn't currently um
something that can talk to me it can
talk to me through the perspective of
somebody who's doing a lot of
interpretation
right we might get to the level where
we're going to be able to coordinate
much more efficiently and much better
towards goals that represent us now Carl
likes to say that the mistake of social
media was hyper connecting us uh not
just hyper connecting us to um a variety
of different um tools because we're
constantly on our phones on our
computers it also hyperconnected us to
um to each other and that that's not
necessarily a good thing it's it can be
good in some cases but in most of the
cases it creates a lot of noise noise
that you weren't always meant to hear um
oh yeah exactly right like being on
Twitter is Hell everybody knows it and
yet you're kind of addicted right you
can't pull away from it because it's a
super stimulus we we need this kind of
input we have been we we we've evolved
to get this kind of input but the
problem is now we're super connected way
too fast we have not evolved the
capacity to pull this information in
properly so it's disrupting all of us so
what if we had this sort of virtual
layer that is very representative of you
right because your agent or an agent
that you have access to Will organize
around you it will become kind of like a
digital twin of you if not perfectly a
digital twin of you it's more like
something that resembles you but has its
own uh volition or its own sense of self
and these agents are capable of pulling
information much faster at at a much
higher um frequency than you and they'll
be able to communicate with each other
pull the right information and feed it
into a higher level generative model
that will be able to integrate all this
information I think we're leading
towards the potential for something very
very beautiful but only if we all have
input into how it moves forward rather
than the very few um who currently
already control everything yeah okay so
there's a couple of things to to really
touch on there um because I wanted I
want to come back to this last point
that you just made but you know that's
really really it's fascinating to me to
think about um you
know having this agent that is so
personally um involved in your own
Consciousness basically but can parse
all of this data because that is that is
such a problem I mean even with even
with what you're talking about with the
amount of data that we we face every day
you know and all of these all of these
algorithms in all these social media um
sites and and different things I mean
they're they're so aggressive in trying
to capture your attention and maintain
it and you know I've joked with friends
that I open my phone to just check the
weather and before I know it I'm down
all these rabbit holes and it's 20
minutes later I'm like I just wanted to
know the weather so yeah being able to
have um being able to have uh like an
intelligent agent who can you know help
to take that noise out of your you know
your Mainframe
life you know I mean that that's really
important especially because I think
that we have a lot of issues these days
that um you know kind of stem from this
overload you know we've never had more
mental health issues you know um we've
you know I think that we're not meant to
be this overwhelmed um and I think it's
taking its toll on a lot of people and
then no go ahead go ahead no I mean
that's part of a research I did as well
on social media and prediction error
with Bruno Lara and Alejandra sria where
basically we're showing that social
media is geared
towards giving you the feeling that
you're minimizing free energy at a rate
that is incomparable anywhere else which
means that now all of your focus is
pulled on this one spot that constantly
is a super stimulus and it also imp es
everything else around you because you
lose the capacity to deal with the
affordances around you in the world
because you you get habituated to this
this new rate of decrease of free energy
um but the problem
is it's not the healthy stuff that gets
pushed by the algorithm it's the stuff
that catches your attention it's on
that's on purpose and the stuff that
catches your attention generally is
stuff that will alarm you right like if
you if you are more alarmed you're more
likely to pull your to pull your
attention towards the thing which is
alarming and keeps you on edge right so
um there's a an epidemic of uh younger
people that are very much more on social
media than we were when we were young
and um it's having a real effect on
their mental health because they're
seeing terrible news or um hyper
filtered people uh or people that tell
them that they need to put on more
makeup that they need to be skinnier
like again these are super stimuli right
the person that I'm that the the
algorithm is going to show you is the
person that is most likely to be on the
extreme end of anything so you're always
going to feel like the only thing that
exists and the only thing that has value
is this extreme end so yeah it is it is
um yeah you know and the other side of
that too with these algorithms is that
they they give you a false sense of
reality because they they cater to
whatever you like whatever you do and I
know some of the algorithms are more
aggressive than others like Tik Tock is
I think probably one of the uh worst
offenders in that way you know like and
and it's when you talk about the young
young people you know like you have kids
that they see something and they click
on it just out of pure curiosity and
then all of a sudden that's all they're
getting in their feed and so it starts
to distort your um your sense of
what is you know most important or most
magnified in the world you know your
your world model really gets messed up
um and I think that that too is why we
see people you know like in these social
media Realms I mean things have gotten
so
aggressive uh just among the
communication with people because people
are are getting fed this sense of um
confirmation for their
opinion and and starting to think that
the rest then the there's few people out
there who disagree with them so they
they're standing firm you know like and
it's it's so Twisted precisely I mean
this that's part of the research we also
did it's called epistemic communities
under active influence and that was one
of the things we showed that um
confirmation bias is natural and it is
reinforcing the phenomenon of echo
Chambers but social
media give rise to this by their very
nature not just because of the algorithm
but also because of their U mechanisms
to pull your attention like for instance
the push notifications they are
constantly dragging you back and so
let's imagine that you are in your
normal uh Network you have people that
agree with you and people that disagree
with you now people that agree with you
are less likely to say anything because
it again it doesn't trigger them so
you're going to get less of that input
but you are going to get a lot of people
that disagree with you because they are
triggered by what you just said they're
triggered by um something that they're
seeing all the time and because of
social media seems very Salient to them
and so what this is going to lead to is
because you don't want to constantly be
triggered because it's too much
eventually you start calling that
population you remove those people so
Facebook was a prime example of this you
could block people yeah so you blocked
people from your uh environments from
your surroundings sometimes even your
own family and you created a bubble that
agreed with you because I mean you can't
constantly deal with a fight you can't
constantly be angry you have to pull
away from social media um and that's
just the Dynamics of the attention
mechanism that's not even the Dynamics
of the algorithm itself that is going to
show you things which you're likely to
engage with um so that's not just TiK
ToK by the way Tik Tok is a big one um
because we we talk about it a lot
because there's geopolitics involved as
well but you does the same thing
Instagram does it Facebook does it all
social media essentially tries to get
you to engage in a way that's not
necessarily healthy for you that's not
one of their concern their concern is
that you um acrew profit for them which
means you're going to stay on the video
or stay on the content watch the ads and
potentially engage with the Creator yeah
yeah so true so this kind of is a nice
say way into a discussion about empathy
because you know all of I I feel like I
feel like all of these uh social
technologies have kind of steered us
into this uh breakdown of empathy in
society and you know I'm curious where
you see that uh kind of Shifting or
changing uh maybe uh in this next era of
advancement of Technology you know given
the research that you're involved in and
where you see that heading with AI and
everything else uh you know what what is
your prediction Where What Where do you
see this
heading so I think a lot of people are
talking about the issue of AI alignment
um people are very afraid because it's
growing very fast faster than we thought
um it doesn't seem to be under anybody's
real control and we are giving the sheen
to AI of a Godlike entity I think I
think even Sim Alman said we are
creating God or something like that and
if we consider an understanding of God
to be somewhat omnipotent uh and omnis
and omniscient sure we're creating
something that resembles that that um
potential uh definition right or at
least that's that's their idea of the
goal I think that's taking the problem a
little bit wrong first alignment isn't a
universal thing no none of us share the
exact same morals there's always
extenuating circumstances to anything
you could find as well this is something
everybody agrees we shouldn't do you can
always find a loophole not everybody
will agree on the loophole but you can
always find one which means even in the
in the in the beliefs that we think we
share with everyone we disagree so we
can't have alignment with just one
person or just one type of alignment
yeah you know I actually saw saw
something uh recently and it was really
interesting because it was like nobody
sees the same thing you do even if
they're looking at the same thing you
know they don't you know yeah precisely
I mean that's that that was the work
with scripts right what we showed is
that scripts are polyus which means even
when you and I are very similar right we
probably share a lot of the same scripts
we're probably going to interpret them
ever so slightly differently yeah so
even in that case you can't create
something that follows one set of norms
because even if it tried to follow one
set of norms because you can't Define
every single action you can always go go
on more granular in time right there's
always going to be a gap between the
request and the
outcome because of that Gap and because
of the fact that not all of us can agree
and perhaps we shouldn't perhaps there
is some space for differing practices
because we should be a little bit
different we should compute the world a
little bit differently alignment can be
taken that way
so if we reframe a little bit the
problem as in how do we make sure that
whatever we
create doesn't destroy us we should
start couching the problem in different
terms one if you're talking about
sentients because AGI is sentient or at
least that's in the definition perhaps
we shouldn't be talking about it in
terms of
subjugation right because if it's sent
in then maybe it shouldn't be a slave
maybe it should be co-creating with us
once we start pulling away from the
Frameworks of adversity of of of
subjugation
violence perhaps we're leaning towards a
potentially good outcome because there
is no good outcome that can come from a
system that understands that has the
capacity to understand that it was
subjugated so let's start over there now
okay so we can't tell it what to do
really we can ask it we can interact
with it we can coordinate with it
harmonize with it all right so we need
to understand it and it needs to
understand us once we reach that point
we start understanding that this is just
like interacting with you and me we I
can't tell you what to do I can just
understand what you want Express what I
want and we can coordinate around these
things and that requires empathy we need
to be able to understand each other on
that profound of a level but I think
it's not just understanding it's really
empathy because the second part of
empathy is why don't I want to hurt you
if it benefits me sure some people do
and in general we have laws to try to
ensure that we don't get to that point
but people still break laws like laws
are not foolproof you can you can try to
encode laws as much as you can it'll get
you pretty far but it won't get you
everywhere you need we as humans have an
inbuilt system that keeps us in majority
pro-social and that's the fact that I
can feel your
pain when I'm when I know that you are
hurting that you are in Dire Straits I
hurt too and I don't want to hurt so I'm
going to probably do something that
helps or I'm going to keep you in a
place where you are happy too now again
that's not fullprof there are people who
are capable of dehumanizing others and
therefore losing sociopaths are a real
thing exactly sociopaths are a real
thing so what are we trying to do we're
trying to create a nons sociopathic AI
an AI with empathy an AI that has the
concept of pain and understands that it
can cause it to you and when it does it
feels something as well so does that
require Consciousness then um right
because I mean the thing is is then it's
just mimicking but if it if it's just
mimicking then it doesn't feel so where
where's that line for you in all of
this so I know I've read some of the
research that you and Maxwell have been
involved in in in the Consciousness area
so I'm I'm just so so curious to take
this there yeah absolutely so um I don't
think necessarily that it's going to
require Consciousness or like let's
assume it is conscious in the AGI
framework then yes we can talk about it
but I think in the sense you don't need
Consciousness to necessarily have
empathy or at least not what we
understand of Consciousness I think we
need a self model and the isomorphy
of feelings and by that I mean
not the exact same phenomenology because
you can empathize with you know a dog
you can empathize with anything really
that's why we have anthropomorphization
we're capable of EMP empathizing with
the moon right right the moon doesn't
feel what we feel but we're still
capable of thinking that there are
commonalities and that given what we
understand to be common goals or goals
that we would have had given a similar
path
something feels either good or feels bad
we have this process of emotional
inference so I think what an empathetic
AI needs is first emotional inference
that's for sure um it needs to have the
capacity to um understand what is an
emotion what what you feel so then it
needs theory of mind it needs to be able
to put itself into your shoes to get
theory of mind it needs sophisticated
inference it needs to be able to place
itself in a different belief State and
from that belief State move the needle
along and and for each action that it
takes adopt the belief state that you
would have given that position um and so
by you what we really mean is it's
understanding of
your model right because it it's not
going to have homonculi it's not going
to believe
it's not going to have a little U that
it's going to carry and that's that's
why we have empathy empathy allows us to
just project our own model into
different belief space without having to
compute entirely different models for
somebody else multiplied by the number
of people that you know that's just
impossible computationally it would be
so expensive that you wouldn't be able
to maintain it you wouldn't be able to
have empathy so here what we have is the
system capable of recognizing an
isomorphism between its current state
and its possible States and your
possible States understand which goals
you might have in common given your
paths and once you have
that understand what it might be doing
to you relative to these goals and why
what it might be doing is pulling you
away from your preferred goals in this
sense interesting okay so I I have
another question then because this is
something that I've been thinking about
recently you know and and what you're
talking about is the possibility of uh
creating these agents training up these
agents with the ability to have empathy
and when I look at humans there are
humans with varying degrees of empathy
you know I don't know if you're familiar
with like um you know the highly
sensitive person personality um you know
it really is a thing um and I didn't
even learn this until like a year or so
ago um but there's something it's
sensory perception
um what is it called but it's basically
like sensory perception overload and
some people and I think it's like maybe
10 to 15% of the population actually is
highly sensitive to um you know sensory
input and and things like that and I
know I'm one of them I just didn't know
it was actually like called something
but like I'm I'm the person who you know
I have to cover my eyes in movies you
know if there's violence because I feel
it if I watch Like boxing I feel the
punches you know I don't just like go oh
that must hurt it's like I feel it um I
feel like my my hearing and my smell and
you know all of my senses are are really
um you know like highly attuned and they
say that like the reason why there's a
percentage of people who are like that
is because back in you know old times
you know those were the people who were
able to sense danger coming you know
there was a reason for having this um
highly you know tune
sensitivity which we really don't
necessarily need so much for Survival
anymore but it's still
there so I'm wondering with these agents
you know do you see that we're going to
maybe even attune these agents to have
different levels of sensitivity for this
type of of stuff because that that to me
leads to an increased sense of empathy
people with high sensitivity are usually
way more empathetic you know more empath
kind
of you know so do what are your thoughts
on any of that do you see that spilling
into this synthetic intelligence you
know sphere or do you see that as
staying kind of just specific to
humans you're talking it is about what
you're talking about is an intensity in
the signal right you're
say you're perceiving the same thing but
really intensely which means you're
really um putting aside all other
signals that would allow you to stay in
the current moment you're really pushing
all other beliefs aside and sometimes
that's useful and required so um when
you're for instance uh talking to
someone who is going through a lot
should you be thinking
about your dishes or should you be in
the moment with that
really empathizing with what they're
going through or someone for instance
who did something that you just cannot
comprehend like it it it
defies your mom and but but everybody
deserves empathy right It's just
sometimes it's hard to give it in those
cases having a more tuned empathy might
help because you might actually be able
to understand had I been in those shoes
I most likely would have made the same
choice it's not an excuse but it dispels
this sense of dissonance with our own
model which keeps us from understanding
and moving forward um so I don't think
we will give them the right level of
empathy I think the systems will
self-organize to use the right level of
empathy for the right type of task or
for the right type of relationships that
they're going to entertain we
unfortunately do not have such minute
control over ourselves uh we can train
we can use coping mechanisms to cut
ourselves off like for instance closing
your eyes right we can cut off sensory
input um but those are but that's
because our model is relatively
transparent to us we don't know what
dials to really push we just know there
might be dials and sometimes when you do
this they get pushed I think it depends
on how we craft the systems if we give
them opacity over themselves they might
um be able to push and pull on certain
dials um and perhaps what we want to
create is systems that have this opacity
perhaps we don't because again we might
be afraid if we if we allow them to
become sociopaths which might be the
simpler options they might become
sociopaths and therefore we don't want
to give them this kind of opacity so um
it's all about what kinds of coping
mechanisms they might use in order to
move the dial a little bit maybe we will
decide uh this system should be very
very empathetic this system should be a
little less empathetic but in the end we
want self-organization as well maybe
some systems will self- select right
maybe they will decide well I am more
empathetic therefore I'm more suited for
that task and I'm less empathetic and I
should be over here yeah you know that's
that's a really interesting way to uh to
look at it um because you know to me it
does kind of make sense that if they
have that capacity of it and like what
you were talking about earlier in the
sense that you know they will be able to
uh
recognize a a
situation understand how to parse all
the data involved Beyond how even we can
interpret a situation um and so yeah
they probably will be able to uh just
tune it in however the to according to
situational need
and I was going to say hopefully they
will be uh
good at
it but but you know if you follow the
train of thought of them developing and
and uh you know self-organizing
self-evolving then it does kind of make
sense that they would get to that point
where they will become extremely good at
at um situational awareness and being
able to you know uh act
accordingly I mean that's kind of the
goal of active inference right
absolutely and it also gives you a sort
of Weir sense of embodiment like for
instance we consider to be embodiment to
be very um carbo
Centric in the sense that we believe
that a body is flesh right or a body is
a physical thing you can touch because
to us that's what embodiment means but
if we sort of abstract away from that
embodiment really is just your
relationship between your boundary and
the world the boundary can be defined in
many many ways it doesn't have to be
defined in physical terms and so once
you start thinking about embodiment that
way you also understand that these
virtual agents through this identity
through this way that they are perspecti
and unique and have what could resemble
a self-determined purpose they now have
a form of embodiment and that also gives
us the capacity to negotiate and to
understand where they might might be
coming from because without embodiment
there's no perspective and there's no um
there's no way to truly have a part of a
model that we can understand properly oh
I really really like that so embodying
embodiment has nothing to do with the
shell you know when you think of of
matter you know and everything on a
physics perspective I mean you know
everything is kind of a facade I mean
nothing is really solid nothing is you
know so even the the body that
we inhabit you know it's it's it's not
necessarily what it seems you know so
that makes a whole lot of sense to me
that embodiment is actually way deeper
than that you know um and that these
synthetic uh intelligences these
intelligent agents then have a it really
comes down to that sense of self that
you were
describing that's really fascinating to
me I love that um okay so uh maybe let's
talk uh for a minute about some of the
challenges and benefits that you see in
the near future with um maybe just in
the evolution of this technology and
then maybe in separately in how how it's
going to affect us as humans and and how
we just live our lives and interact with
each other uh one of the challenge I see
is trust it's going to be difficult to
get everyone to potentially trust a
system that we don't even trust yet
ourselves right we're still talking
about alignment in those terms so we
don't even trust it um it's going to be
difficult to scale certain parts of our
approaches um as you can already see the
llms are so expensive that they can't
just be built by anyone which leads us
to power struggles and power dynamics
which certain groups that already have a
monopoly being able to control what we
even have access to and who gets
represented so there's all these um
sociopolitical aspects to the models
that are going to arise and this is
going to give rise to potential larger
political unrest which we are already
seeing with um people who are governing
us who do not quite understand what is
going on what the technology is we don't
even have precedence for this uh we're
going to rely
on whoever says they're experts so it's
it's not a given that they're going to
rely on the experts and who can even
really say that they are the expert this
is an emerging field right uh and the
fact that you're a technological expert
does not mean that you are a
sociological experts on the outcomes of
a model that you created so what we're
going to need is interdisciplinary
approaches to ask ourselves collectively
very complex questions and we're going
going to have to do so in a coordinated
manner that follows or at least is at
the same Pace as the political actions
and then we're going to have to think
about how this allows people to leverage
a technology that has the potential to
either revolutionize our very approach
to reality
or um put us in a in a very complicated
position relative to um Capital
production uh and resource uh production
as well because if robots can do all
your work for you and you only really
only need one human uh for five 10 100
robots it becomes a really crucial
question who gets to use resources and
how so all of these questions are
happening at the same time not all the
parties are discussing and it's possible
currently that some of the parties
discussing are discussing more on the
front of an economical arms race than
really necessarily thinking about the
people that are going to be um affected
so I think this is the main challenge
yeah um no I I agree with that so then I
I'm curious just on that note you
know who do you see you know because I
know it has to be a variety of um
different types of people that are are
kind of coming to this consensus of you
know governance structure right I mean I
know that we've we've seen some really
good plans for governance and and
technologies that can code guidelines
into the agents but those guidelines
have to be structured first they have to
be agreed upon so you know if it's not
going to be the tech Elite and it's not
necessarily going to be governments you
know because everybody's going to have
their own agenda that maybe isn't the
best for human civilization moving
forward and the people moving forward
who do you should be part of this
conversation you know um how diverse do
you see it and you know what is missing
in these
conversations so first I think we need
to educate everyone everyone needs to
have a thorough understanding of what is
going on and what are the potential
effects on their lives and what kind of
avenues they have to affect the outcome
so that's one big part but that's true
for everything now I was part of an
initiative to disc
um to not focus group exactly but to
discuss with uh citizen
participants what they want to see how
they want to see it help Etc right so I
think there's the possibility to go pool
from every population as much as
possible people who are willing and
interested in participating in the
conversation amassing these results and
then bubbling that up to the governing
bodies that can then create the
appropriate committees to continue
pulling these in these um information
these opinions these perspectives and
combining them with that of experts from
a variety of different fields experts
which will have to
then understand the specific effects or
uses of AI in their respective field
because I can't predict how um say the
field of construction is going to get
affected by AI I don't have the right
level of expertise but there are people
in the world who too so we need to make
sure that these people get brought into
the conversation at the right time um
with the right understanding and with
the right other actors to have the the
correct kind of discussions to ask the
right questions and come up with the
right set of Standards or approaches or
even create participant initiatives to
use AI in the ways that they would need
it yeah and maybe you know um as we
start to see all of these smart cities
become developed and you know I know
that there's some wonderful people that
are working on um ensuring that when we
move into this space of of Automation
and smart cities that we're talking
about inclusive sustainable smart cities
all of you know all of these things that
are going to be you know really
important to uh the way
we the way we live uh in the future so
and the way the way we live and and you
know uh Cooper at in cooperation with
all of this technology so um and we we
have a really unique um opportunity
right now to move into this space that
is more inclusive that actually is for
the benefit of
humanity and it all depends on the
decisions that we're making right now so
uh I agree with you I I think that it it
requires committees all over and in in
in all different sectors and for all of
them to be able to have
input now how viable that
is that's the question right because you
know um it seems to me you know
historically
speaking that doesn't always that
doesn't always work out but but we are
moving into this space where governance
as a whole even even the way you
know our our world is structured with
governments you know has the opportunity
to shift and change you know we we we're
embarking on a real interesting uh time
in human history so I really hope you
know I really hope with what
you're you know along the same lines of
your opinion that we do move into this
space that is more um aligned with with
the needs of people not necessarily
power you
know yeah so okay okay so then that was
a great
challenge uh what about benefits you
know what are the benefits that you
see honestly they're endless um let's
imagine a world where work is not the
center of our lives where work is
something that happens and that you can
do if you want if you want to find
purpose and helping others if you want
to innovate or try different things you
can but you don't have to that it's not
a condition for your Survival Let's
understand a new world where maybe you
have free time maybe you have time to
connect with others Find meaning in your
life that's not derived from you know
doing what your boss wants uh or staying
in traffic for four hours a day or this
sort of thing you know so that's I think
it's hard to deprogram a lot of people
from thinking that work is purpose and
that your life is only given meaning
because of the work that you do but
let's imagine a world where you could
right yeah that and that's such a great
point because you know I think as humans
you know we're wired you know everybody
wants to make a difference right but you
know we've been programmed to think that
the majority of our time has to be spent
really scratching and cling for
survival you know this is fun it's a
really modern invention like we actually
like um hunter gatherers used to work
roughly for like 4 hours a day that that
was their sweet spot and in the medieval
times um it was something very similar
where their productive time was around
four hours a day because they would
arrive on the SES they would you know be
provided food by their uh by the people
who hired them they would eat for an
hour they would work then they would eat
lunch again another hour um sometimes
when it was too hot they would take a
nap and start working again if it was a
very long day and then they would eat in
the evening like they would eat a lot
and most of this eating took a lot of
their day which means their productive
time really was just four to five hours
a day and it was a very a much more
natural way to go about things it it it
enabled people to really connect to not
be completely spent nowadays you're
expected to be productive for eight
hours and then you have no time once
you're home you're exhausted you can't
you can't really exist as a human we've
forgotten that existence is supposed to
be what we want to make of it what we
are trying to fulfill if you're
religious maybe spend more time with
your religious peers be more spiritual
if you're scientific read more connect
more with other Minds like yours there's
so many things you could be doing other
than just working yeah and you know it's
interesting because I I really think
that um you know we as we move into this
next phase of high Automation and the
you know jobs will look a lot different
probably go away will we will find
meaning in other ways you know and and
to me I feel like just that stage alone
is gonna it'll set the stage for
increased empathy and and things like
that because I think you know I also
think that technology as we move more
into this space where we are more
aligned with the technology and then
we're going to start kind of having a a
glimpse into you know other people very
closely as well their thoughts their
their desires their fears and and all of
that and I feel like all of this is
going to give us this opportunity to um
instead of be so self-focused you know
we'll be able to look outward we'll be
able to really you know focus on our
communities more focus on the people in
our lives
um yeah I I definitely I know I know it
sounds very utopian you know I I say
that a lot but to me I see that that is
a a very real uh possibility yeah and
it's a necessity too a lot of us have
lost complete touch with others the
isolation in urban centers is so so
pronounced that people are more and more
depressed even though they are living
with millions of other people around
them we have lost a lot of our social
fabric for good reasons some of it
needed to happen right but we have to
reconstruct some of it because social
connection wasn't the problem it was the
means by which we were using this or
manifesting this social connection that
was problematic now we need to
reconstruct communities to support say
our elders to have a real social fabric
that can help raise children can help
each other like some people can't even
cook for themselves not that they they
don't have the money not that they don't
have the food they just don't even have
time they're working all the time and
it's because the current structure is
made for a a nuclear family but first
families don't have to be nuclear
families can be very complex and and and
networks of people that help each other
also you don't have to consume all the
time if you have someone that can help
you and do things and has something you
can leverage each other for the
resources that you have so the this
social fabric needs to come back we are
headed to a cliff if we don't I think
this is a beautiful opportunity and if
we can really allow our each other to
connect with the people we want to
connect with connect with people who
maybe share the same values or share a
piece of knowledge that we want to
acquire or feel some emotions that we
are feeling at the same time like for
instance movies that we love I don't
have to know whether you're a Democrat
or Republican to enjoy the same movie as
you and and bask in the joy of that
right um if we have the capacity say to
understand each other's language without
having to necessarily learn it you can't
learn 50 languages some people can most
people don't even have the time to do
that but we can communicate across those
languages now we have the technology to
do that right so there's so much
possible in terms of human connection
through this technology that if we don't
lose sight of that could head to
something that resembles your version of
your
Utopia yeah I love that those are all
great points and you know I I share that
vision and and I think maybe that's a a
great place to kind of um stop uh today
I I think that's a great note to leave
this on okay now H how can people reach
out to you how how can they get in touch
with you so they can easily find me on
LinkedIn uh they'll find my name easily
I respond to most messages and if they
do read one of my papers they can find
my email there and send me any inquiry
they have okay awesome and I'll put your
LinkedIn uh in the the show notes and
Mal thank you so much for coming on our
show today and uh you know I would love
to continue this conversation in the
future and and you know as all of the
the progress with your research unfolds
and uh thank you again thank you so much
for being here thank you for having me
all right and thanks everyone for tuning
in we'll see you next
[Music]
time